Guide to the W. A. Swanberg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
W. A. Swanberg Papers
1927-1992.
Swanberg, W. A., 1907-
36 linear ft. (81 boxes, 80 document boxes and 1 record storage carton).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#1219
4078385
History
Biographer and historian; author of books about Morgan Dix, Theodore Dreiser, Dorothy Elmhirst, James Fisk, William Randolph Hearst, Henry Luce, Joseph Pulitzer, Daniel E. Sickles, Willard D. Straight, Norman Thomas, Flora Payne Whitney, Williams C. Whitney, and the American Civil War. He won the Pulitzer Prize for biography in 1973 for "Luce and his Empire" and the National Book Award for biography in 1977 for "Norman Thomas: The Last Idealist." He also wrote many magazine articles on crime.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, notes, memoranda, notebooks, notecards, proofs, photographs, microfilms, and printed materials. The Papers include the manuscript research materials and correspondence for each of his books except his biography of Theodore Dreiser. Among the correspondents are William Benton, Bruce Catton, Carey McWilliams, Mrs. Fremont Older, and Thornton Wilder.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into four series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts and Project Files
Subseries III.1: Articles and Short Stories
Subseries III.2 Books
Subseries III.3: Unpublished Book Materials [RESTRICTED]
Subseries III.4: Manuscripts by Others
Series IV: Subject Files
Subjects
Time, inc.; United States.--Office of War Information.; Xerox Corporation.; Anderson, Eleanor Copenhaver, d. 1985.; Auchincloss, Louis.; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-; Benton, William, 1900-1973.; Cain, James M. (James Mallahan), 1892-1977.; Carlson, Chester Floyd, 1906-1968.; Catton, Bruce, 1899-1978.; Dix, Morgan, 1827-1908.; Dowdey, Clifford, 1904-1979.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Elmhirst, Dorothy Payne Whitney Straight.; Fisk, James, 1835-1872.; Floyd, John B. (John Buchanan), 1806-1863.; Fowler, Gene, 1890-1960.; Goldberg, Rube, 1883-1970.; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951.; Hearst, William Randolph, 1908-1993.; Hersey, John, 1914-1993.; Hobson, Laura Keane Zametkin.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977.; Johnson, William E. (William Eugene), 1862-1945.; Leech, Margaret, 1893-1974.; Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967.; McCullough, David W.; Macdonald, Dwight.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; McWilliams, Carey, 1905-1980.; Miller, Merle, 1919-1986.; Nevins, Allan, 1890-1971.; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Older, Fremont, Mrs., 1875-1968.; Powell, Dick, 1904-1963.; Pulitzer, Joseph, 1847-1911.; Randolph, A. Philip (Asa Philip), 1889-1979.; St. Johns, Adela Rogers.; Salinger, Pierre.; Sickles, Daniel Edgar, 1819-1914.; Smith, H. Allen (Harry Allen), 1907-1976.; Stout, Rex, 1886-1975.; Straight, Willard Dickerman, 1880-1918.; Strauss, Anna Lord, 1899-1979.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-1977.; White, Theodore H. (Theodore Harold), 1915-1986.; Whitney, Flora Payne.; Whitney, William C. (William Collins), 1841-1904.; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975.; Fort Sumter (Charleston, S.C.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Biography--19th century.; Espionage.; Journalism.; Newspaper publishing.; Newspapers.; Periodicals--Publishing.; Prohibition.; Propaganda, American.; Publishers and publishing.; Spies.; Tobacco industry.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; Xerography.; Advertising.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Card files.; Diaries.; Fiction.; First drafts.; Galley proofs.; Illustrations.; Interviews.; Lists.; Manuscripts.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorandums.; Microfilms.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photographs.; Poems.; Proofs.; Scrapbooks.; Short stories.; Speeches.; Authors, American.; Biographers.; Businessmen.; Capitalists and financiers.; Clergy.; Inventors.; Journalists.; Newspaper editors.; Novelists, American.; Periodical editors.; Prohibitionists.; Retired military personnel.; Socialists.; Soldiers.; World (New York, N.Y.: 1860-1931)
Access Restrictions
Boxes 69-78 are closed to all use.
Acquisition
1984 Papers Swanberg, W.A. Gift
09/09/93 M-93-09-09 Papers Swanberg, John W. & Sara V. Gift
Gift of W.A. Swanberg, 1984.
Gift of John W. Swanberg & Sara V. Swanberg, 1993.
Related Material
Materials relating to Theodore Dreiser are at The University of Pennsylvania Library.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Anderson, Eleanor G.C. (Mrs Sherwood).
  - Auchincloss, Louis
  - Baldwin, Roger Nash
  - Barzun, Jacques
  - Benton, William
  - Cain, James M.
  - Catton, Bruce
  - Dowdey, Clifford
  - Fowler, Gene
  - Goldberg, Rube
  - Hearst, Millicent W. (Mrs William R-.}
  - Hearst, William Randolph
  - Hersey, John
  - Hobson, Laura Z.
  - Hoover, J. Edgar
  - Hutchins, Robert M.
  - Leech, Margaret Kernochan (Mrs Ralph Pulitzer
  - McCullough, David
  - Macdonald, Dwight
  - MacLeish, Archibald
  - McWilliams, Carey
  - Miller, Merle
  - Nevins, Allan
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold
  - Nixon, Richard M.
  - Older, Cora Miranda Baggerly (Mrs Fremont)
  - Powell, Dick
  - Randolph, Asa Philip
  - St Johns, Adela Rogers
  - Salinger, Pierre
  - Smith, H. Allen
  - Strauss, Anna Lord
  - Stout, Rex
  - Untermeyer, Louis
  - White, Theodore Harold
  - Wilder, Thornton
- Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - American Heritage (Box 1)
  - Citizen Hearst (Box 1)
  - The double life of the Rev. Dr. Greenway (Box 2)
  - First blood (Box 2)
  - Jim Fisk (Box 2)
  - Luce and his Empire. (Box 2)
  - Luce and his Empire, 1946-1967 (Box 80)
    (correspondence with Mary Bancroft)
  - Norman Thomas (Box 2)
  - Norman Thomas (Box 3)
  - Pulitzer (Box 3)
  - Scullin, George, 1931-1992 (Box 79)
  - Sickles the incredible (Box 3)
  - Swanberg, Jackson, 1955-1965 (Box 79)
  - Tobacco manuscript (Box 3)
  - Whitney father, Whitney heiress (Box 3)
  - Agents (Box 4)
    - Constance Smith Associates, 1954-1962 (Box 4)
    - McIntosh and Otis, Inc., 1963-1977 (Box 4)
  - Publisher: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1955-1977 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, A - Z (Box 4)
  - A (Box 46)
  - B (Box 46)
  - Burgum, Ralph (Box 46)
  - C (Box 46)
  - Columbia University (Box 46)
  - Contemporary Authors (Box 46)
  - Cooley, Hal (Box 46)
  - Cooley, Hal (Box 47)
  - Cooley, Don (Box 47)
  - D (Box 48)
  - Dempewolff, Richard F. (Box 48)
  - Dougherty, Jane Holtzlander (Box 48)
  - E (Box 48)
  - Eddy, Bob (Box 48)
  - F (Box 48)
  - G (Box 48)
  - H (Box 48)
  - Hertsgaard, Palmer J. (Box 48)
  - Holtzlander, Scott & family (Box 49)
  - I (Box 49)
  - J (Box 49)
  - K (Box 49)
  - L (Box 49)
  - Layne, Hugh (Box 49)
  - Lee, Allan G. (Box 49)
  - M (Box 49)
  - McIlvaine, William D. (Box 49)
  - Mclntosh and Otis Literary Agents (Patricia Schartle Myrer & Constance Smith) (Box 50)
  - Mahoney, Tom (Box 50)
  - Minnesota, Univ. of and Minn. Historical Society (Box 50)
  - Mitchell, Burroughs & Jean (Box 50)
  - Modern Maturity (Box 50)
  - N (Box 50)
  - O (Box 50)
  - P (Box 50)
  - Pearson, John F. (Box 50)
  - Peel, Roy Victor (Box 50)
  - Peterson, Albert E. (Box 51)
  - Quintard, Elise Katherine (Box 51)
  - R (Box 51)
  - Rascoe, George (Box 51)
  - S (Box 52)
  - Sagendorph, Kent (Box 52)
  - Scribner's (Box 52)
  - Stedman, Alfred D. (Box 52)
  - Swanberg family (Box 52)
  - T (Box 52)
  - U - V (Box 52)
  - U.S. Government (Box 52)
  - U.S. Office of War Information (Box 52)
  - W (Box 52)
  - Y (Box 52)
  - Yoken, Melvin B. (Box 52)
  - Young, Robert, Jr. (Box 52)
  - Unidentified and Miscellaneous (Box 52)
- Series III: Manuscripts and Project Files
  - Subseries III.1: Articles and Short Stories
    - American Heritage; the magazine of history
      - "1890." The Nineties, circa 1967 (Box 5)
        (contains carbon copies of manuscripts and a printed copy of the magazine)
      - "Lord of San Simeon." about William Randolph Hearst, 1961 August (Box 5)
      - "The spies who came in from the sea," about World War II espionage, 1970 April (Box 5)
        (contains manuscripts, notes, proofs, and a copy of the magazine)
      - "Was the Secretary of War a traitor?" about John Buchanan Floyd, 1963 February (Box 5)
        (contains manuscripts and copy of the magazine)
    - Saga Magazine
      - "The most successful sinner." (about Robert Irving Latimer, Jr.), 1950s (Box 14)
        (on the verso of notes for Jim Fisk.)
      - "The question of Eileen's pajamas," (about Eileen Gibson & James Camb), 1950s (Box 14)
      - "Strangler Jack's night on the town." (about Jack Grace & William Anthony Grace), 1950s (Box 14)
      - "Arnold Schuster"s Tragic Reward" (Box 79)
    - Stories for True Magazine (Box 79)
    - Stories for Cavalier Magazine (Box 79)
    - Book reviews (with related correspondence) (Box 57)
    - Can you spare a dime? (Box 57)
    - Cassie Chadwick case (Box 57)
    - Chicago's Kid from Powder River (Box 57)
    - Dark angels, desperate deities (Box 57)
    - Diaries, 1934-35. (Box 57)
    - Diaries, 1944-45. (Box 57)
    - Dictionary of American Biography Marion Davies (Box 57)
    - The Draw-a-Blank Club (Box 57)
    - The enemy is listening (Box 57)
    - Fighting the Nazis with a valet (Box 58)
    - Going home dirty (Box 58)
    - Growing old recklessly (Box 58)
    - John S. Knight biography (Box 58)
    - Just ask Mr. Delacorte (Box 58)
    - Modern Maturity: Love on a shoestring (Box 58)
    - The Pierce-Arrow predicament (Box 58)
    - Poetry (Box 58)
    - Scandal a la mode. [Col. William d'A. Mann] (Box 58)
    - School papers & notes (Box 58)
    - Short stories--early, (17 Folders) (Box 58)
    - Some things that happened (Box 58)
    - True: Koretz, Leo (Box 58)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 58)
    - Articles-- General, 1939-1960 (Box 79)
  - Subseries III.2 Books
    - Citizen Hearst, 1961
      - Illustrations (Box 6)
      - Manuscripts (Box 6)
        (first draft)
      - Manuscripts (Box 7)
        (final draft and articles)
      - Notes (Box 8)
        (interviews, notebooks, notecards)
      - Printed materials (Box 9)
        (copy of book, proofs, clippings, pamphlets, magazines)
      - Card file Box (Box 60)
      - Typescript (Box 61)
        (printer's copy)
      - Lists (Box 61)
      - Printed materials (Box 61)
        (reviews, articles, advertisements, etc.)
    - The double life of the Rev. Dr. Greenway, 1958
      (unpublished)
      - Manuscripts (Box 10)
      - Notebook (Box 10)
    - Dreiser, 1965
      - Typescript (Box 62)
        (carbon copy of final draft)
      - Typescript (Box 63)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 63)
      - Advance Publicity-- Advertising and Reviews, (2 Folders) (Box 79)
    - First Blood: The Story of Fort Sumter, 1957 (Box 63)
      - Manuscripts (Box 10)
      - Notes and Illustrations (Box 11)
        (notebooks, notecards, photographs, & typescripts)
      - Printed Materials (Box 12)
        (copy of book, pamphlets, clippings)
      - Typescript (Box 64)
      - Notes (Box 64)
      - Printed Materials (Box 64)
        (Scrapbook of reviews, etc.)
    - Jim Fisk: The Career of an Improbably Rascal, 1959
      - Manuscripts (Box 13)
      - Notes and Illustrations (Box 14)
        (notebooks, notecards, photographs and typescripts)
      - Printed Materials (Box 14)
        (galley proofs, copy of English edition)
      - Printed Materials (Box 64)
    - Luce and His Empire, 1972
      - Manuscripts (Box 15)
      - Manuscripts (Box 16)
      - Notes and Memoranda (Box 16)
      - Notes and Memoranda (Box 17-19)
      - Notebooks (Box 20)
      - Notecards (Box 20)
      - Speeches and Writings, 1920-1939 (Box 20)
      - Speeches and Writings, 1940-1956 (Box 21)
      - Speeches and Writings, 1957-1969 (Box 22)
      - Proofs (Box 23)
      - Printed Materials (Box 24)
        (copy of book, magazines, clippings etc.)
      - Typescript (carbon copy of final draft: "3rd copy") (Box 65)
      - Notes (Box 65)
      - Printed Materials (Box 65)
      - Advance Publicity (Box 80)
      - Magazines (Box 80)
      - Reviews (Box 80)
      - Pulitzer Prize (Box 80)
    - Norman Thomas: The Last Idealist, 1976
      - Manuscript (Box 25)
      - Manuscript (Box 26)
      - Notes and Memoranda (Box 26)
      - Notes and Memoranda (Box 27)
      - Notebooks (Box 27)
      - Notes from the New York Public Library (Box 28)
      - Printed Materials (Box 29)
        (clippings, copy of book, pictures, proofs, etc.)
      - Notes (Box 65)
      - Newspaper Reviews (Box 79)
      - National Book Award, 1977 (Box 79)
      - Publicity (Box 79)
    - Pulitzer, 1967
      - Illustrations (Box 30)
      - Manuscript (Box 30)
      - Manuscript (Box 31)
        (final draft)
      - Notes (Box 31)
      - Notes (Box 32)
      - Notebooks (Box 32)
      - Notes and Correspondence (Box 33-34)
        (Xerox copies)
      - Printed Materials (Box 35)
        (clippings, copy of book, pamphlets)
      - Galley Proofs (Box 35)
      - Typescript (Box 66)
        (carbon copies)
      - Printed Material (Box 67)
        (Reviews, etc.)
    - The Rector and the Rogue, 1968
      - Manuscripts (Box 36)
      - Notes (Box 36)
      - Printed Copy of Book (Box 36)
      - Typescript (Box 67)
        (carbon copy)
      - Summary (Box 67)
      - Reviews (Box 81)
    - Sickles the Incredible, 1956
      - Manuscripts (Box 37)
      - Illustrations (Box 38)
      - Notes, Memoranda, copies of letters (Box 38)
      - Notes, Memoranda, copies of letters (Box 39)
      - Notebooks (Box 39)
      - Notecards (Box 39)
      - Printed Materials (Box 40)
        (magazine and copy of book)
      - Galley Proofs (Box 40)
      - Printed Materials (Box 67-68)
    - Tobacco Manuscript, 1961
      - Manuscript (Box 40)
      - Notebook (Box 40)
      - Notecards (Box 40)
      - Notes (Box 40)
      - Printed Materials (Box 40)
    - Whitney Father, Whitney Heiress, 1980
      - Manuscripts (Box 41-42)
      - Illustrations (Box 43)
      - Notes and Memoranda (Box 43)
      - Notes and Memoranda (Box 44)
      - Notebooks (Box 44)
      - Printed Copy of Book (Box 45)
      - Proofs (Box 45)
      - Galley Proofs (Box 68)
        (Xerox copies, marked)
  - Subseries III.3: Unpublished Book Materials [RESTRICTED]
    - Chester Carlson Biography
      - Typescripts (Box 69)
        (two drafts)
        closed to all use
      - Notebooks (Box 69)
        (three volumes)
      - Printed Materials (Box 69)
      - Notes and Correspondence (Box 70)
        - Bliss, Howard H., & Riverside College (Box 70)
        - Caltech (Box 70)
        - Carlson, Chester Floyd (Box 70)
        - Carlson, Dorris (Box 70)
        - Carlson, Roy W. (Box 70)
        - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (Box 70)
      - Delson/Guyana (Box 70)
      - Dumond, Laurence (Box 70)
      - Edison, Thomas A. (Box 70)
      - Kornei, Otto (Box 70)
      - NYLP Notes (Box 70)
      - Parapsychology (Box 71)
      - The Peninsula Association for Retarded Citizens, Inc. (Box 71)
      - The Piney Woods Country Life School (Box 71)
      - Twogood, Archie J. (Box 71)
      - Walkup, Lewis E. (Box 71)
      - Xerox/Haloid (Box 71)
      - Zen, etc. (Box 71)
    - William Eugene "Pussyfoot" Johnson Biography
      - Typescripts (Box 72)
        (many drafts)
      - Typescripts (Box 73)
      - Typescripts (Box 74)
      - Microfilms (Box 74)
      - Notes and Correspondence (Box 75)
      - Bradford, Jane W. (Box 75)
      - Nethercut, Constance Stanley (Box 75)
      - Pictures (Box 75)
      - Printed Materials (Box 75)
      - "Pussyfoot" (Box 75)
      - Scripts (Box 75)
      - Notes (Box 76)
      - Notes (Box 77)
      - Notebooks (Box 77)
      - Photographs (Box 77)
      - Notes (Box 78)
      - Scrapbooks (Box 78)
  - Subseries III.4: Manuscripts by Others
    - Cooley, Harold E. (Box 59)
    - Feld, Ross C. (Box 59)
    - Horowitz, Terry Fred (Box 59)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - Addresses (Box 53)
  - The Authors Guild, Inc. (Box 53)
  - Awards (Box 81)
  - Biographical (Box 53)
  - Dell Publishing and George T. Delacorte (Box 53)
  - Durant, Will (Box 53)
  - Financial and Royalty Information (Box 81)
  - Heritage Village, Newtown, CT (Box 53)
  - Humor and Miscellaneous (Box 53)
  - Minnesota, University of (Box 53)
  - National Book Award (Box 54)
  - P.E.N. (Box 54)
  - Photographs (Box 81)
  - Publicity (Box 81)
  - Prize Committees, 1971-1979 (Box 81)
    (includes files from the Pulitzer Prize Award Committee, National Book Award Committee and the Van Wyck Brooks Committee)
  - Religion (Box 54)
  - The Society of American Historians, Inc. (Box 54)
  - U.S. Office of War Information-- Documents and Miscellaneous (Box 54)
  - U.S. Office of War Information-- Magazines and Pamphlets (Box 55)
  - U.S. Office of War Information-- Newspapers (Box 56)